Okay
בוקר טוב Boker tov everybody. Today is of course יום השואה, Yom
HaShoah, so the learning should be in the memory of those who
gave up their lives who were murdered in the שואה. Shoah.
We start with the משנה Mishnah at the bottom of ע"ב עמוד
ב, Ayin Bet Amud Bet, and we obviously are now going from
the משנה Mishnah that dealt with things that a woman could do,
a wife could do that would be the basis for divorce, and
divorce with cause, divorce without paying the כתובה. Ketubah. And now we
move on to another, this is obviously a סוגיא Sugya that becomes
very important in discussions because one of the issues was the issue
of head covering, which we mentioned yesterday, went through it a little
quickly unfortunately, but of course the basic idea as we said then
was that the position of the משנה Mishnah specifically around the issue
of norms of behavior of married women, specifically about drawing
the attention of other men was specifically the problem, and very different
from a discussion in ברכות Berachot which speaks about hair as a
type of an ערוה, Erva, a nakedness. This one specifically was not
absolute, it was related only to married women, only in public
contexts, questions of community in somebody's courtyard where other people were present
as long as it was not considered like a very public type
of a place. It preferred to emphasize the head, not the hair,
so there's a lot of very important things that come up from
this גמרא. Gemara. And of course one of them is the גמרא's
Gemara also discussion about whether it is norms of Jewish women, and
then the question is what happens if those norms change, or is
it דת משה, Dat Moshe, which could be understood to be a
biblical obligation or at least a biblical norm, and then becomes the
question about what if the norms of society change, how much is
that could the idea of דת משה Dat Moshe change as a
result as well. So those are all very important questions relating to
the issue of head covering for women, but now we go on
to the next משנה Mishnah which deals with a which will get
us into a סוגיא Sugya which is extremely important relating to contemporary
עגונה Agunah issues or possible עגונה Agunah solutions. So let's take a
look now at the משנה Mishnah on the bottom of ע"ב
עמוד ב. Ayin Bet Amud Bet. המקדש את האשה על מנת שאין
עליה נדרים. HaMekadesh et HaIsha al menat she'ein aleha nedarim. A man
marries a woman, קידושין, Kiddushin, betroths, so we're not yet with נישואין,
Nissuin, which is the focus of our מסכת. Masechet. On the condition
that she has not made any vows, that she does not have
any נדרים Nedarim binding upon her. ונמצאו עליה נדרים, V'nimtze'u aleha nedarim,
and then afterwards it turns out that she does have vows binding
upon her. אינה מקודשת, Eina mekudeshet, so she's not married. It was
a קידושין על תנאי, Kiddushin al tnai, on a condition. The condition
wasn't met, so the קידושין Kiddushin is not binding. Yeah, yeah, exactly.
He says he verbalized he verbally says it.
כנסה סתם, Kinusah Stam, now he brought her in, meaning this is
the נישואין, Nissuin, the focus of this מסכת, Masechet, not קידושין. Kiddushin.
So he brings her in without saying anything explicit, so it's not
קידושין, Kiddushin, it's נישואין, Nissuin, and nothing explicit was said. ונמצאו עליה
נדרים, V'nimtze'u aleha nedarim, and it turns out that she has vows.
תצא שלא בכתובה, Taitze shelo beKetuvah, she is divorced and she doesn't
get a כתובה. Ketubah. So the fact that now the question that's
going to arise in the גמרא Gemara is is this building on
the previous case? It sounds like it is. It sounds like I
would think the simple sense of the משנה Mishnah is he already
explicitly said at the time of the קידושין Kiddushin that he doesn't
want her to have any vows on her and he did it
only on that condition,
and therefore it's if it turns out and but then he went
ahead and he married her without repeating the תנאי. Tnai. He did
the נישואין סתם Nissuin stam without reiterating it. And so because he
had verbalized the תנאי Tnai earlier, it's clear that he cares about
this, so he's entitled to divorce her without a כתובה, Ketubah, תצא
שלא בכתובה. Taitze shelo beKetuvah. But on the other hand, he might
still need to divorce her because the נישואין Nissuin took place without
him reiterating
the
תנאי. Tnai. So that is a probably the simplest way of reading
that משנה, Mishnah, but this leads into a very important debate of
רב ושמואל Rav veShmuel in the גמרא Gemara that the other possible
way of reading it is that well a man betroths the woman
קידושין Kiddushin and the נישואין Nissuin and he didn't say anything. He
just married a woman and it turns out she has נדרים, Nedarim,
and a woman who has נדרים Nedarim binding upon her even if
a man never articulated anything is enough of a problem to say
that he's entitled to divorce her without a כתובה, Ketubah, תצא שלא
בכתובה.
Taitze shelo beKetuvah. As long as it's something that he can't מפר
mefer himself, right?
Well, you can't מפר mefer if it was made before you got
married.
Okay, like the news item from the other week, a woman found
out a woman had been married nine times before her marriage nowadays,
and they didn't know it.
be a little bit more problematic than just having a שמועס shmus
with a guy now and again. Okay. על מנת שאין בה מומים,
al menas she'ein ba mumin, similarly, similarly, he said he's marrying on
the condition to have no blemishes, however blemishes are defined. והתקדשה v'is-kadsha
and there they were discovered, so that was a marriage on condition.
Condition wasn't met. He's not married. But that was the betrothal stage.
כנסה סתם k'nasa stam then he had the נשואין nisuin without saying
anything.
Then the question is does it mean that it was preceded by
the קידושין בתנאי kidushin bitnai or the whole thing was סתם. stam.
But okay, now they're married and he didn't say a תנאי tnai
at the time of
the נשואין. nisuin. ונמצאו בה מומים v'nimtze'u bah mumin and there are
blemishes. תצא שלא בכתובה. teitzei shelo bichtuvah. He can be divorced without
paying the כתובה, ktuvah, but she still needs to be divorced.
כל המומים הפוסלים בכהנים פוסלים בנשים. kol hamumim haposlim bakohanim poslim banashim.
What type of a מום? mum? If he didn't say, specify what
type of a מום, mum, what would be considered a מום? mum?
The same things that constitute מומים mumim by כהנים kohanim which is
quite an extensive list. One would imagine there might be different things
which are relevant. But if he didn't say anything, we go by
that standard. Okay, so גמרא gemara says as to the רישא. reisha.
How do you define? Oh, you mean by the מומים? mumim? Well,
it adds how would you define מומים. mumim.
No, but in other words, that's about מומים. mumim. But the עיקר
ikar of the משנה mishna is about the תנאי tnai he had
at the קידושין בתנאי. kidushin bitnai.
Right. So the תנאי tnai was right. But I mean it adds
it for the sake of telling you how to define מומים mumim
in that case. And I assume also that part B of what
עיקר ikar added the fact that if the whole משנה mishna is
talking about anything סתם stam that there was never תנאי tnai if
in one part about תצא שלא בכתובה teitzei shelo bichtuvah is when
the whole process was סתם. stam. So just because it says that
a woman with vows is a basis for divorce without a כתובה
ktuvah doesn't mean a woman with מומים mumim is the basis for
a divorce without a כתובה, ktuvah, right? I mean so there's a
חידוש chiddush there, right? If you articulate the תנאי tnai it's less
of a חידוש. chiddush. But if you didn't articulate the תנאי tnai
in the second half of each of these clauses, then the חידוש
chiddush is that even without a husband saying anything, vows is a
problem. Even without husband saying anything, blemishes are a problem. Okay, so
now the גמרא gemara says like this. ותנן נמי גבי קידושין כי
האי גוונא. v'tnan nami gabei kidushin ki hai gavna. We have a
similar משנה mishna by קידושין, kidushin, actually literally the same משנה mishna
in מסכת קידושין. masechet kidushin. So the גמרא gemara says הכא כתובה
איצטריכא ליה. hacha ktuvah itztricha lei. התם קידושין הכא כתובה. hatam kidushin
hacha ktuvah.
Here,
the point of the משנה mishna is to tell you the clause
about the כתובה, ktuvah, that he can divorce her without a כתובה.
ktuvah. So it tells you the first half about that the קידושין
kidushin itself isn't binding in order, you know, but the focus is
on the second half, that when it goes to the נשואין nisuin
stage there's no כתובה. ktuvah. So it taught כתובה ktuvah for the
point of the כתובה ktuvah part of the משנה. mishna.
התם איצטריכי ליה קידושין. hatam itztrichi lei kidushin. קידושין איצטריכי ליה. kidushin
itztrichi lei. The משנה mishna is taught for the purpose of telling
you that the קידושין kidushin isn't binding in the first
clause. ותנא כתובה אטו קידושין. v'tana ktuvah atu kidushin. And since it's
teaching you about that the קידושין kidushin isn't binding, it mentions the
second clause as well, that if they go through to the point
of the נשואין, nisuin, there also won't be a כתובה. ktuvah. So
you're right, it's the exact same משנה mishna and it's needed in
מסכת קידושין masechet kidushin to talk about קידושין בתנאי kidushin bitnai and
it's needed in מסכת כתובות masechet ktuvos to talk about when do
you get a כתובה ktuvah without, you know, when you get divorced
without
a כתובה. ktuvah. Okay. אמר רבי יוחנן משום רבי יוסי בן יהוצדק.
amar rabbi yochanan mishum rabbi yosi ben yehotzadak. באלו נדרים אמרו. be'elu
nedarim amru. Which by which vows? The משנה mishna tells you what's
considered a מום mum if it wasn't specified. What's considered a vow
if it wasn't specified? Do we mean all vows? It just said
vows. So say no, not all vows. Just like the following types.
שלא תאכל בשר ושלא תשתה יין ושלא תתקשט בבגדי צבעונין. shelo tochal
basar v'shelo tishteh yayin v'shelo tiskashet bivigdei tzevonin. If you want, you
recall, you remember that these were lists that the גמרא gemara said
earlier were considered, you know, עינוי נפש inui nefesh according to one
תנא. tanna. תניא נמי הכי. tanya nami hachi. באלו נדרים אמרו דברים
שיש בהן עינוי נפש. be'elu nedarim amru dvarim sheyesh bahen inui nefesh.
And there you go, affliction of the soul of the of the
body. שלא תאכל בשר ושלא תשתה יין ושלא תתקשט בבגדי צבעונין. shelo
tochal basar v'shelo tishteh yayin v'shelo tiskashet bivigdei tzevonin. So presumably things
that were considered less serious than this would not be weighty enough
to be a problem of vows. Okay, so the גמרא gemara says,
בעי מיניה רב פפא. ba'ei mineih rav pappa. Rav Pappa asked, אהיי?
ahei? Which clause of the משנה mishna is this going on? אילימא
ארישא? ilima areisha? The
first part when he explicitly says on condition you don't have vows.
כיון דקא קפיד אפילו כל מילי נמי. keivan d'ka kafid afilu kol
mili nami. Since he said explicitly on the condition you have
no vows, so that means any vow. אלא אסיפא? ela asifa? Must
be going on the second part. And he's reading the second part
that they never stipulated anything, the קידושין kidushin and נשואין nisuin without
anything stipulated, and it turns out she has vows, that's a basis
for divorce. For that case we didn't stipulate anything, um, that would
be, it has to be vows at at least a certain threshold.
But if he explicitly said no vows, no vows means no vows.
So the גמרא gemara says רב אשי אמר. rav ashi amar. Rav
Ashi disagrees. לעולם ארישא. l'olam areisha. No, it's going even in the
case where he explicitly stipulates and says no vows.
Okay. מיהו דקפיד אינשי הוי קפידא. mihu d'kafid inshi havei kfeida. Who
even if he said no vows, still, we can interpret what that
means. The type of things that people normally are, like, concerned about,
that's a legitimate concern. הוי קפידא קפידא. havei kfeida kfeida. His concern
is legitimate. מיהו דלא קפדי אינשי mihu d'la kafdi inshi things that
are trivial that normal people aren't concerned about. So long's it's trivial,
we don't assume that it's to be true that even if he
explicitly is concerned, that's not legitimate to say that's true. It doesn't
explicitly say you can't have any vows, I don't care how trivial,
you can't have any vows, and if you do, I'm not marrying
you, then of course that's binding. A person can make any stipulation
they want, right? So they can do it on the condition that
you have six toes, I mean, people could make any conditions. But
if he's saying it without being specific, we are not going to
interpret that, we're not going to interpret it to include things that
normal people don't care about. Okay, so even if he explicitly says
on condition of no vows, we're only going to say things that
normally be a type of a thing that people would care about.
Yes?
I understand
why עינוי נפש Inuy Nefesh really means an עינוי נפש Inuy Nefesh
for her. So the real question is why should it matter for
him? But you know, I guess it could be something to the
effect of how much you know, how much it's
you know, it's a shared relationship, like what she eats, you know,
and what affects the, you know, affects what's going on, you know,
within the marriage. But you're right. I mean עינוי נפש, Inuy Nefesh,
עינוי נפש Inuy Nefesh means it's an עינוי נפש Inuy Nefesh for
her. That's for her. That's, but now why it should matter that
it's an עינוי נפש? Inuy Nefesh? But look, who wants somebody that's
always like, you know? Like some people feel like what, I'm going
to be married to this person that every day they've got this
new food fad? One day it's veganism, the next day it's you
know, it's this, the next day it's
macrobiotics, right? You know what's next? Alright, so moving on.
Right, exactly, exactly. There's a sense of shared life, shared experiences. Can't
go out to restaurants, I want to go to my steakhouse. Alright
anyway, move on. Now we get to again, yeah yeah, now
we get to the issue that is like you know sort of
the central question of this משנה, Mishnah, which is a big issue
in הלכה. Halachah. Let's take a look. איתמר, Itmar, it's taught. קידשה
על תנאי, Kidsha al tnai, the קידושין Kiddushin was done on a
condition, וכנסה סתם, U'chensah stam, and the נשואין Nisu'in was done without
anything being articulated. Okay, which is very possibly the way it is
in the משנה. Mishnah.
What's the הלכה? Halachah? Do we assume that the תנאי Tnai that
was said at the time of the קידושין Kiddushin remains in effect
at the time of the נשואין Nisu'in if it was not repeated
at that time? So רב אמר Rav amar צריכה הימנו גט. Tzricha
heimenu get.
If you don't repeat it at the time of the נשואין, Nisu'in,
then once the נשואין Nisu'in took place, they're married regardless of any
תנאי Tnai that was said at the time of the
קידושין. Kiddushin. ושמואל אמר U'Shmuel amar אינה צריכה הימנו גט. Eina tzricha
heimenu get. שמואל Shmuel says you don't need a גט. get. Since
at the time of the קידושין Kiddushin the תנאי tnai was articulated,
if the קידושין Kiddushin never took effect because the תנאי tnai wasn't
satisfied, then why should the fact that just because they slept together
it doesn't matter? They're sleeping together, but it's only קידושין Kiddushin based
on the area, the giving of the ring. And if the giving
of the ring was not a binding act of קידושין Kiddushin because
of the תנאי, tnai, then sleeping together is just sex. It's not
a binding act of
קידושין. Kiddushin. Okay? No no no, the תנאי tnai wasn't satisfied. The
תנאי tnai wasn't satisfied. Okay, so that's the question. I mean, if
it's only discovered later, okay, that's the point. At the time they
have the נשואין, Nisu'in, he still doesn't know whether it was or
wasn't, it was discovered later. Okay, so that's the case. The ring
was given on a condition, it'll turn out later, we discover later
that the condition wasn't met, and then they have the נשואין Nisu'in
and they slept together. So רב Rav says once they slept together,
that's it, they're married. ושמואל, U'Shmuel, we're about to see, and שמואל
Shmuel says no, if there was no קידושין, Kiddushin, then afterwards they
remain not married. So let's take a look.
אמר אביי, Amar Abaye, here's אביי. Abaye. Don't think that רב's Rav
reason is that since you went ahead with the נשואין Nisu'in and
you didn't bother to repeat it, at the time of the נשואין
Nisu'in you didn't say, 'Remember I said this is only going to
be a marriage if you don't have מומין.' mumin. So since he
didn't repeat it, it shows that at this stage he's like forgotten
like he doesn't care about it anymore and implicitly he's waiving the
condition. Okay, which is interesting because the קידושין Kiddushin happened a year
ago and if that was never binding because the condition wasn't met,
who cares if a year later he waives the condition? Like that's
an interesting idea that a year later he could say forget about
the condition and then retroactively they were married a year ago when
he gave her, you know, when he gave her the ring. That's
like an interesting idea but you could waive it after the relevant
act took effect. But that's what you might think, that since he
went ahead with it and didn't repeat it, it shows that he's
sort of saying forget about the condition and now retroactively the giving
of the ring is what was binding. was binding. But that's just
position. There's gonna be a lot of interpretations of the debate of
רב Rav and שמואל. Shmuel. This is his read of the position
of רב. Rav. So he says I don't think רב'ס Rav's position
is because he waived the תנאי tnai and retroactively the giving of
the ring was binding. That's not it. אלא טעמא דרב, Ela ta'ama
deRav, the reason of רב Rav is שאין אדם עושה בעילתו בעילת
זנות she'ein adam oseh beilato beilat zenut
because the original giving of the ring was not the marriage, okay,
because the תנאי tnai wasn't met. But now that they're having sex,
the act of sex is an act of קידושין. kiddushin. One of
the ways that you get married is through an act of sex.
And, okay, but who says he wanted it to be an act
of קידושין? kiddushin? Maybe it's just an act of sex. No, we
would assume that a person does not want his act of sex
to be a simple act of fornication. He wants it to be,
he wants it to be marital. It doesn't mean that anytime people
are found having sex, it's oh, you're married, because שאין אדם עושה
בעילתו בעילת זנות. she'ein adam oseh beilato beilat zenut. It means in
this context where clearly they had a חופה, chuppah, they had a
קידושין, kiddushin, they had this, it's clear that the act of sex
he wanted at this point to be, he wanted to be in
a marital context. And therefore, because he wants that, we would say
that at this moment he wants this act to be an act
of קידושין kiddushin regardless of whether that condition was met or not,
because the consequence of it not being an act of maintaining his
condition would mean that it could be that he's actually having illicit
sex. And people, so since he would not want to risk having
illicit sex, therefore we will say that at this stage he no
longer cares about it, not so that the previous thing is what's
meaningful but so that this act of sex becomes an act of
קידושין. kiddushin. Okay. And so that's
why, why does it matter this reason he gives? Either way it's
binding. Well, one interesting נפקא מינה nafka mina is, when do you
say they're married from? Right? Were they married from a year ago
or were they married from now? There could be נפקא מינהs nafka
mina in terms of monetary issues and other types of issues and
whatever. Like, let's say, you know, I don't know, let's say she
went ahead and she slept with another man between the קידושין kiddushin
and the נישואין, nisuin, right? When are they married? Were they married
from the קידושין? kiddushin? Were they married from the נישואין? nisuin? That's
like a very, you know, relevant type of an issue. And there's
something else here that's at stake as well which is, you know,
which is the question about and this is not explicit in the
גמרא Gemara but this is a major discussion of the אחרונים, Acharonim,
which is, does it really mean that the man is thinking to
himself, or at least we'll say, even if he's not explicitly thinking,
we'll say that what he's thinking is, I want this to be
an act of קידושין kiddushin because I wouldn't want, you know, because
I wouldn't want it to be an illicit act of sex. Or
do we say it doesn't matter, you don't need כוונה, kavannah, a
more radical read than this, you don't need כוונה kavannah for קידושי
ביאה. kiddushei biah. You know, other things, giving the שטר, shtar, giving
money, you'd have to give, it sort of like it has to
be a formal act of קידושין kiddushin and you need the intent
that this should effect קידושין. kiddushin. Maybe קידושי ביאה kiddushei biah is
any sex done in the marital context, even without intention of קידושין,
kiddushin, automatically is defined as קידושין. kiddushin. Now, that's a nice למדנות'ס
lamdanus's approach, the problem with it is הלכה-ically halacha is that it
would create huge problems in terms of עגונה agunah and גיטין gittin
because it means any couple that's living together as a married couple,
right, even if they never had a legitimate קידושין, kiddushin, would הלכה-ically
halacha be considered married and they would need a גט. get. So
that is a, there's ways of limiting it, but that's a type
of an approach that some אחרונים Acharonim take which has very broad
implications. But anyway, the way we're doing it as the גמרא Gemara
says is it's not like retroactively he waived the תנאי tnai because
he didn't repeat it or the lack of repeating means you waived
it. No, that קידושין kiddushin didn't take effect, but this act either
we have to define, do you want this to be an unconditional
act of ביאה biah or you know, do you want this to
be a ביאת קידושין biat kiddushin or would you want it to
be conditional? Presumably he would want it to be unconditional and to
be married because he wouldn't want it to be illicit sex.
Right. Let me clarify something because in a normal situation so to
speak is קידושין kiddushin plus נישואין. nisuin.
And then at the time of נישואין nisuin
is ביאה. biah. Here the
whole thing, the ביאה biah is קידושין, kiddushin, exactly. It's co-terminus with
the נישואין? nisuin? Yes, so קידושין kiddushin and
נישואין nisuin are taking place together right now. Now normally it's true,
you could have
קידושי ביאה kiddushei biah and then נישואין nisuin with a second act
of ביאה biah so to speak.
Normally there would be two acts. There would be קידושי ביאה kiddushei
biah and a year later you'd have the חופה chuppah and you'd
have נישואין. nisuin. But here the קידושי ביאה kiddushei biah is taking
place like in the חתן'ס chasan's home and it's done in a,
right, it's sort of taken at the same time. Now, okay, so
that's רב'ס Rav's position, okay.
Now, אלא טעמא דרב שאין אדם עושה בעילתו בעילת זנות. Ela ta'ama
deRav she'ein adam oseh beilato beilat zenut. So the גמרא Gemara says
הניחא Haniicha and שמואל Shmuel disagrees. שמואל Shmuel says the condition is
still binding, not only was he not מוחל mocheil the תנאי tnai
but even The act of sex is not an act of קידושין,
kiddushin, everything is based on the original תנאי. t'nai. So the גמרא
Gemara says הא פליגי בה חדא זימנא. Ha p'ligi bah chada zimna.
They already argued on this once before. דאיתמר, De'asmar, it was taught,
קטנה שמיאנה והגדילה. ktana shemi'ana ve-higdila. קטנה, ktana, remember that if the
mother or brothers can marry her off, obviously she doesn't have a
father when she's a minor, and she has the opportunity to reject
her husband while she's still a minor. Now, she didn't reject her
husband. Okay, so there was only a דרבנן derabbanan קידושין. kiddushin. והגדילה,
Ve-higdila, and now she's an adult. And after she became an adult,
she's all twelve years old, she continued to live with her husband
and she sleeps with her husband. Okay, but they never had a
prior act of קידושין, kiddushin, but now they've been sleeping together in
the marital context of an adult. So as an adult, she can
marry herself off. Okay. עמדה וניסת, Amda veniset, and then she goes
ahead and she marries another man. רב Rav אמר amar אין צריכה
גט משני. ein tzaricha get mishani. She doesn't need a גט get
from the second guy. The fact that she continued to live with
her husband and have sex in a marital context means that that
is קידושין kiddushin to the first husband and that act of sex
is binding. And she committed adultery? Well,
if she has sex with the second guy, but okay, that's true,
but let's say she just had קידושין, kiddushin, let's make it easy,
let's say נישואין. nisuin. Okay. So רב Rav says any קידושין kiddushin
with the second guy is completely not binding. Her act of having
sex with the first guy in a marital context means she's married
to the first guy.
ושמואל u-Shmuel אמר amar צריכה גט משני. tzaricha get mishani. No, she
needs a גט get from the second guy. Even though she was
having sex with the first guy in a marital context, there was
no act of קידושין kiddushin that preceded it. So שמואל Shmuel says,
no listen, here's the way to frame it. Okay. If a woman
has sex based on a marriage that preceded it, okay, there's a
marriage that preceded it and then she has sex with the same
guy obviously, okay, how much is whether she's married all based on
whether the original קידושין kiddushin was binding or not? Okay. So רב
Rav says even if the original קידושין kiddushin was not binding, right,
because it was בתנאי bitnai or because it was when she was
done by her mother and brothers when she was a קטנה, ktana,
it doesn't matter. Marital sex within the marital context, even if the
original קידושין kiddushin was not binding, is itself, does itself make her
married. Okay. That's what רב Rav says. And therefore in this case
she won't need a גט get from the second guy. Okay. In
the other case, she needs a גט get from the first guy
because the sex in a marital context is binding. Whereas שמואל Shmuel
says no, it's all based on the original קידושין. kiddushin. If the
original קידושין kiddushin wasn't binding because it was בתנאי bitnai or because
she was a קטנה, ktana, then the sex that takes place afterwards
also doesn't make her married. What? It is binding מדרבנן, miderabbanan, isn't
it?
If she's a קטנה.
ktana.
That's fine, that's rabbinic, but not דאורייתא. de'oraisa. Yeah.
So you're not going to kill her because of...
yeah, exactly. And she also needs a גט, get, whatever, let's say
she needs a גט get מדרבנן, miderabbanan, let's not worry about that.
Okay, fine. So the גמרא Gemara says like this. Okay. So you
see that that's the same debate, whether it all goes by the
original קידושין kiddushin or not. Okay. Maybe that's an easier way there
to frame the debate, you know, do we say, you know, כל
הבועל אדעתא דקידושין הראשונים בועל kol habo'el ada'ata dekiddushin harishonim bo'el or
something of that nature. So the גמרא Gemara says like this. Okay,
so the גמרא Gemara says why do you have to tell it
to them twice? The גמרא Gemara says צריכא, tzricha, you have to
tell it to them twice. אי איתמר בהא, Ei itmar be-ha, if
it were said in the case of the
קטנה, ktana, בהא קאמר רב, be-ha ka'amar Rav, that's where רב Rav
says that the continued having sex together is considered married. Why? משום
דלא איכא תנאי, mishum dela ika t'nai, there's no תנאי. t'nai. אבל
בהא, aval be-ha, in our case, דאיכא תנאי, de-ika t'nai, where there
is a
תנאי, t'nai, אימא מודי ליה לשמואל eima modei lei le-Shmuel that the
sex would be considered like an act, that the sex would be
dependent on the original marriage. Now why should it be that the
articulation of a תנאי t'nai or the presence of a תנאי t'nai
makes a difference?
So רש"י Rashi says that because רש"י Rashi focuses on, you know,
that the guy has כוונה kavana that the act of sex be
an act of קידושין. kiddushin. But if he's saying a תנאי, t'nai,
there's a very strange approach of רש"י, Rashi, I think it's strange.
If there's a תנאי, t'nai, that means that he's assuming that everything
is okay. And he says the תנאי, t'nai, she never said
anything, so, and he says I told her I didn't want it,
she didn't say that she had it. So when it comes time
for the act of sex, he's assuming there's no problem. So if
he's assuming there's no problem, he doesn't bother having כוונה kavana that
the act of sex should be an act of marriage. So therefore
I might think that in the case of תנאי, t'nai, it's more
likely that the ביאה, biah, that they're not married, because he doesn't
realize he has to have the intent that it should be an
act of marriage. That's a little convoluted. I think it's a much
simpler point, which is the question is how much does the original
marriage, the legitimacy of the original קידושין kiddushin frame whether this act
of sex, you know, is considered marriage or not. So if nothing
was said with קידושי קטנה, kiddushei ktana, so okay, technically it wasn't
binding, it was קידושי קטנה, kiddushei ktana, but they continued to live
together as a married couple. If they continued living together as a
married couple, it itself creates the קידושין. kiddushin. Whereas if he explicitly
says "I don't want you to have any vows,"... but he continues
to frame their continued living together as a married couple. So even
though they're continuing to have sex, he explicitly put on the table
that this is a scenario you don't have vows. So therefore, it
would continue to if he binds that have vows, that continues to
frame that act with where they're continued living together would not be
a act of marriage.
Yes. Can children make
vows, underage, a minor?
Yeah, no, but we're not... I mean the reference is 11, but
those are two separate cases. The vows are for an adult and
the minor. Those are the two cases. In each case, it wasn't
binding. One because he made a condition and one because she was
a minor.
And if she made one as a minor, would it be valid
when she becomes an adult?
No, no. But these are two separate cases. Okay.
So in these cases where he or she became of major age,
let's say she didn't just sleep with some other guy, she actually
married him, right?
Right. No, no,
the question is she continued to sleep with her first husband.
In both cases, she married a guy and then she continued to
sleep with him even though the קידושין kiddushin wasn't binding. In one
case the קידושין kiddushin wasn't binding because of the condition, of the
תנאי, t'nai, the second case it wasn't binding because she was a
minor. And the question is, is she married to the first guy?
It's confusing because how do you test if she's married to the
first guy? You can test it in one of two ways. If
she wants to leave the first guy, does she need a גט,
get, which is the way our משנה mishna tests it? Or
if she marries a second guy, does she need a גט get
from the second guy? And then the נפקא מינה nafra mina is
the reverse. Okay, but it's a bit confusing that way, but bottom
line, it's the same question: is she married to the first guy?
So why do we have to have the debate of רב Rav
and שמואל Shmuel in both cases: is she married to the first
guy if she continues to sleep with him after a non-binding
קידושין? kiddushin? So the גמרא gemara says that there's a bigger חידוש
chiddush of רב Rav in the case where to say that they're
still married in the case where the reason it wasn't binding initially
was because of the condition. And what I'm saying the reason is
that it's a bigger חידוש, chiddush, not like רש"י, Rashi, is that
when he made the condition explicit,
then he made the problem explicit, there's even more reason to say
that even if they continue to sleep together, it's all still framed
by the original condition. Okay. And if רב Rav says even when
you explicitly say, only on this condition, once you continue to live
together, that itself makes you married, that's a bigger חידוש. chiddush.
So in the קטנה k'tanah case, what are this husband and wife
supposed to do in order to be quote-unquote officially married then?
I mean, according to שמואל, Shmuel, they might want to go ahead
and have a separate ceremony. Okay. Or maybe explicitly say we're doing
ייחוד ביאה yishuv beyah or something. But for רב, Rav, it's not
necessary? Yeah, that happens automatically. Okay. If you only had said it
in the case of the
תנאי, t'nai, that's where שמואל Shmuel says that the continued living together
is not binding. But here, in the case of the minor where
no condition was articulated and they continue to live together,
maybe he would agree to רב Rav that their continued living together
makes them considered married. So we have to have both cases. Now,
our דף daf is, this עמוד amud at least is very short
because of this huge תוספות. Tosafos. And I just want to tell
you that what the huge תוספות Tosafos discusses is another גמרא gemara
that has the phrase which is... in another גמרא gemara there's the
statement which says
אין תנאי בנישואין. ein t'nai benisuin. Okay. Now the reason that is
important is because in our גמרא, gemara, it sounds like even though
רב Rav says once they have slept together, whatever, they're married regardless
of the earlier תנאי, t'nai,
it sounds like it's only because they did it without saying anything,
קנה סתם. kanta stam.
It sounds like according to רב, Rav, if he explicitly said before
the חופה, chuppah, he renounced the תנאי... t'nai... I'm just reiterating now,
this whole חופה chuppah and we and if we continue and when
we go home and we sleep together and have sex, whatever, it's
all still on the condition that you don't have any נדרים. nedarim.
So it sounds like from our גמרא gemara that then it wouldn't
be then they wouldn't be married, right? It's only because he didn't
repeat the תנאי. t'nai. But this other גמרא, gemara, אין תנאי בנישואין
ein t'nai benisuin sounds like in principle, I don't care what you
say, right? Once you start living together, you're married. I don't care
how much you want to make it conditional. So that's a big
נפקא מינה, nafra mina, right? And this is all extremely relevant because
as you might be aware, already going back 150 years with rabbis
in France, one solution to the עגונה agunah problem is just make
all the קידושין kiddushin on תנאי. t'nai. Make the קידושין, kiddushin, you
know, it's all on the condition that it doesn't come about that
we get divorced and I don't give you a גט get or
whatever and you know, those things happen that we get divorced and
I don't give you a גט, get, then you're never been married.
On a תנאי t'nai in the future? Yeah, you can be like,
on the condition that the Mets win the World Series or something...
you can base it on things that happen in the future. So
the problem is that, right, that's what שמואל Shmuel would say... anyways,
so the thing is is that time... that's trying to make a
תנאי t'nai at the time of קידושין. kiddushin. What about our גמרא
gemara that says once they start sleeping together, according to רב, Rav,
it doesn't matter what conditions they have? Well, if you say maybe
it's not an absolute statement, maybe, you know... because you didn't repeat
the תנאי t'nai and maybe you could be explicit and say even
after you start sleeping together, you know, or maybe there are ways
around it in our גמרא Gemara because it's just since תנאי t'nai
wasn't repeated. But in principle a תנאי t'nai would be possible at
the time of, you know, even after נישואין nisuin under the right
conditions. This statement of the גמרא Gemara that says it quotes אין
תנאי בנישואין ein t'nai b'nisuin sounds like it'll never work in principle.
So תוספות Tosafot has a whole discussion is this really true? Maybe
we don't פוסק posek this way? Maybe this just doesn't mean what
as categorically as it sounds? But all of this is extremely relevant
in terms of whether any of this, you know,
could be used as an option as a solution to the עגונה
agunah problem.
If we say אין תנאי בנישואין ein t'nai b'nisuin is that that
absolutely trump anything else that the ביאת נישואין biat nisuin will trump
anything else?
Yeah, no matter how much you want to make it conditional, once
you're having sex together as as that's it. Right. As opposed to
רב Rav who says since you didn't repeat the תנאי, t'nai, right,
well, right exactly.
So let me just get back to what you just said. If
you make a תנאי t'nai like okay, we're נישואין nisuin is only
binding if I give you, you know, if things don't work out
then I give you a גט get and whatever, you know what
I'm saying? And he doesn't and then he's- we're seeing implicitly then
they're both okay with it being a בעילת זנות beilat zenut until
then? Right. And why are they saying some things against that, אין
אדם עושה
בעילתו בעילת זנות?
ein adam
oseh beilato beilat zenut?
No, because we'd say אין אדם עושה בעילתו בעילת זנות ein adam
oseh beilato beilat zenut only if you know מסתמא. mistama. If you
explicitly say you're okay with it being בעילת זנות beilat zenut because
you're making this תנאי, t'nai, because of course our גמרא Gemara was
אין אדם עושה בעילתו בעילת זנות ein adam oseh beilato beilat zenut
was סתמא. stama. I should also say that a number of פוסקים
poskim say that maybe another addressing רב's Rav issue of אין אדם
עושה בעילתו בעילת זנות, ein adam oseh beilato beilat zenut, that that
was when the only type of marriage that was recognized was religious
marriage. In our- in our realities where there's secular marriage and this
couple is recognized by society as married, then it would not be
a בעילת זנות beilat zenut even if or the couple wouldn't perceive
it as a בעילת זנות beilat zenut even if it was not
a binding קידושין. kiddushin. So that's a way of also trying to
argue that maybe a תנאי t'nai could work because maybe you'd argue,
oh, a תנאי t'nai won't work, they won't want it to be
בעילת זנות. beilat zenut. Maybe in today's reality with the secular marriage
also in place they wouldn't perceive it as a בעילת זנות beilat
zenut and therefore it, you know, gives more opportunity for the תנאי
t'nai to work. So one of the issues even רב Rav who
says that the תנאי t'nai is not- does not remain in effect,
it seems to be because of certain assumptions that we make, אין
אדם עושה בעילתו בעילת זנות, ein adam oseh beilato beilat zenut, he
didn't repeat it, which would mean that there might be possibilities where
the תנאי t'nai could be in effect and that's very relevant for
the עגונה agunah issue. This type of a statement seems to be
making a categorical point. This is תוספות Tosafot we're reading in brackets
this from another גמרא Gemara and that's- but that's really very, you
know, relevant in terms of this issue.
Yes. 150 years ago regarding this עגונה agunah issue? Yeah, what happens
to the status of the children?
If the woman doesn't have a גט get and she has- oh,
for- if it's retroactive?
Oh, retroactively they weren't married?
Yeah, nothing, meaning there's no ממזרות, mamzerut, right? No, it's not the
idea like that they have, you know, a bastardy in in secular
society which is a child born out of wedlock. ממזר mamzer is
only a child born through an act of adultery. Right. Okay, so
now the גמרא Gemara says like this.
Okay, so תנאי. t'nai. Now let's see how this debate fits in
our
משנה. mishnah. כנסה סתם ונמצאו עליה נדרים. kensah stam v'nimtze'u aleha nedarim.
So he
married her with a תנאי, t'nai, that's what it sounds like in
the משנה, mishnah, and then the קידושין kiddushin was with a תנאי,
t'nai, and then they have the נישואין, nisuin,
and it turns out that she actually has נדרים. nedarim. תצא שלא
בכתובה. teitzei shelo b'ketubah. She gets divorced without a כתובה. ketubah. Okay,
כתובה ketubah היא דרבנן, hi d'rabbanan, fine, she's not entitled to a
כתובה ketubah because she had the vows and he said I'm on
the condition that there are no vows. אבל גט בעי, aval get
ba'ei, but it says תצא. teitzei. תצא teitzei means like that she
has to be divorced, you divorce her without a כתובה, ketubah, that's
what it means תצא בגט. teitzei b'get. Okay? So it sounds very
explicit from the משנה mishnah like רב, Rav, that once they start
living together his תנאי t'nai is meaningful enough to show
that he's at fault and he doesn't pay the כתובה, ketubah, but
once they actually live together it sounds like she needs a גט.
get. מאי לאו
בדקטרי תנאי, mai lav bid'katrei t'nai, the משנה mishnah sounds like it's
building on a case of תנאי, t'nai, the קידושין kiddushin was on
condition and כנסה סתם kensah stam and the נישואין nisuin was without
being re-articulated
and she's found with נדרים. nedarim. It's a contradiction to שמואל. Shmuel.
So רב Rav says לא לא lo lo that's not the case
in the משנה. mishnah. When it says the second part about סתם
stam it's talking about a different case. כנסה סתם כנסה סתם. kensah
stam kensah stam. It means that nothing was said. Not at the
קידושין, kiddushin, not at the נישואין. nisuin. A simple case. A guy
married a woman and after the חופה chuppah turns out she has
נדרים. nedarim. So a woman with נדרים, nedarim, that's a basis for
divorce, but no stipulation was ever made. Okay, so she needs a
גט get but he doesn't have to pay the כתובה ketubah because
that's a woman with נדרים nedarim is a reason to divorce her
without a כתובה. ketubah. דאמר מר. de'amar mar. Okay, מכלל דבבא מציעתא.
miklal d'baba metzi'ata. Do you have to stipulate or not? Okay. So
what Shmuel wanted, one minute, אבל פשיטא תנאי דקידושין וסתם הכי נמי
דבעי גט. aval pshita tnai d'kidushin u'stam hachi nami d'bayi get. You're
telling me that if the קידושין kidushin was בתנאי b'tnai and then
followed by a נישואין, nesu'in, she would not need a גט, get,
like that's Shmuel's position?
If that's true, I'll tell you the המקדש את האשה על מנת
שאין עליה נדרים ונמצאו עליה נדרים. ha'mekadesh et ha'isha al menat she'ein
aleha nedarim v'nimtze'u aleha nedarim. The משנה Mishnah says if a man
marries a woman on the condition that there's no vows and finds
out vows, אינה מקודשת, eina mekudeshet, it's not binding. So why did
it just give you the case when it was discovered before the
נישואין? nesu'in? Right? Tell me according to Shmuel, tell me a bigger
חידוש, chiddush, כנסה סתם ונמצאו עליה נדרים knassa stam v'nimtze'u aleha nedarim
אינה מקודשת. eina mekudeshet. Tell me if a man does a קידושין
kidushin on תנאי tnai and then you have the נישואין nesu'in and
then it's discovered that the תנאי tnai wasn't, this condition wasn't met,
that she's not married. Why are you telling me that it's discovered
before the נישואין? nesu'in? Right? Tell me according to Shmuel, tell me
the bigger חידוש, chiddush, even after the נישואין nesu'in she would not
be married if it was done בתנאי. b'tnai. So the גמרא Gemara
says, אמר כל שכן הא, amar kol she'ken ha, and surely the
case when it was not yet a נישואין. nesu'in. So the גמרא
Gemara says, you know what? הכי נמי קאמר, hachi nami ka'amar, who's
to say that that's not what the משנה Mishnah is saying? The
משנה Mishnah didn't tell you whether or not there was a נישואין.
nesu'in. The משנה Mishnah says when the קידושין
kidushin is done on תנאי tnai and the תנאי
tnai isn't satisfied, it's not binding, that would be whether or not
there was a נישואין nesu'in or there wasn't a
נישואין. nesu'in. Okay, that's what's in the משנה. Mishnah. הכי נמי קאמר,
hachi nami ka'amar, yes this is what the משנה Mishnah is saying.
המקדש את האשה על מנת שאין עליה נדרים, ha'mekadesh et ha'isha al
menat she'ein aleha nedarim, he does קידושין kidushin on condition
that there is no vows.
Whatever happened afterwards, I mean, the משנה Mishnah is not specifically talking
about there's נישואין. nesu'in. You just say you made a vow at
the time of the קידושין, kidushin, then whatever happens afterwards,
yes נישואין, nesu'in, no נישואין, nesu'in, doesn't matter, she's not מקודשת. mekudeshet.
Right? ונמצאו עליה נדרים אינה מקודשת. v'nimtze'u aleha nedarim eina mekudeshet.
Okay. כנסה סתם, knassa stam, if however there was never a תנאי
tnai articulated to begin with, okay, it was just a simple case
of קידושין kidushin and נישואין nesu'in and then כנסה סתם ונמצאו עליה
נדרים, knassa stam v'nimtze'u aleha nedarim, in that case she obviously needs
a גט get because there was no תנאי, tnai, but she's not
entitled to a כתובה. ketubah. Okay, so Shmuel reads the משנה Mishnah
that the second case does not build on the first, it's independent.
The first case is if there was a תנאי tnai at the
time of the קידושין, kidushin, she's not married regardless of whether there
was or was not a נישואין. nesu'in. If there was no תנאי,
tnai, then there's a גט get but she's not entitled to a
כתובה. ketubah. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this, so in
that case where there's no תנאי tnai articulated, she doesn't get a
כתובה ketubah but she needs a גט. get. So the גמרא Gemara
says, one minute, ומאי שנא כתובה דלא בעיא, u'mai shna ketubah d'la
ba'aya, now one minute, so according to Shmuel, you take the case
in the משנה Mishnah
that he didn't say anything and he didn't say anything, he's entitled
though to deprive her of the כתובה ketubah if he divorces her
because a husband doesn't want a wife with vows, so it's considered
to be like a false divorce and she's at fault. So if
that's true, that we can so much assume that a guy doesn't
want to marry a woman who has vows and therefore he's entitled
to not pay the כתובה, ketubah, why don't we say that therefore
we should assume that he didn't want to marry her in the
first place and it's not binding? So the גמרא Gemara says, ומאי
שנא כתובה דלא בעיא, u'mai shna ketubah d'la ba'aya, how is it
different that why he doesn't have to pay
the כתובה? ketubah? דאמר d'amar because we assume that he
says אי אפשי באשה נדרנית, ee efshi b'isha nadranit, I don't want
a woman who takes vows. אי הכי, ee hachi, so that's why
he's entitled to say I'm not paying the כתובה, ketubah, I wasn't
expecting a wife that has vows. So if that's enough to say
that he doesn't have to pay the כתובה, ketubah, גט נמי לא
תיבעי. get nami lo tiba'ei. Why don't we just say that even
without any תנאי, tnai, the first thing without any תנאי tnai she
doesn't get a כתובה ketubah because she has vows, maybe the marriage
shouldn't be binding, he didn't want a wife who has vows. Okay.
אמר רבה צריכה גט מדבריהם. amar Rabba tzricha get m'divreihem. No way,
really he would need a גט get at all, a woman with
vows, guy doesn't want to marry a woman with vows and therefore
she's clearly קידושי טעות kidushei ta'ut and if she needs a גט
get it's only rabbinically. וכן אמר רב חסדא צריכה גט מדבריהם. v'chen
amar Rav Hisda tzricha get m'divreihem.
One minute, when we say that she's מקודשת מדבריהם? mekudeshet m'divreihem?
All right, let's, I don't know, don't worry about it. רבא אמר,
Rava amar, so רבא Rava says, ספוקי מספקא ליה. sfuki maspka lei.
No, no, it's not a rabbinic גט. get. We're not sure how
bad the נדרים nedarim issue is. A woman who has נדרים, nedarim,
do we assume that somebody, a man would never want to marry
such a woman and it's קידושי טעות kidushei ta'ut and she wouldn't
need a גט, get, or do we assume that, no, a man
and a man would be okay with that? So we don't know
whether it's a binding קידושין kidushin or not. We have a
ספק. safek. Okay, again, no תנאי tnai was made but she has
vows. What do you assume a normal man would normally be okay
with this or not okay, would it be קידושי טעות? kidushei ta'ut?
We don't know. ספוקי מספקא ליה. sfuki maspka lei. לגבי ממונא לקולא,
lgabei mamona l'kula, when it comes to, okay, does he have to
pay the כתובה, ketubah, our answer is no, he doesn't have to
pay the כתובה. ketubah. That's a question of money and therefore we
say המוציא מחברו עליו הראיה. hamotzi mechavero alav hara'aya. If she wants
to collect her כתובה, ketubah, she's going to have to... So what's
the difference between these two שיטות? shitos? No, no, okay, so specifically
regarding ממונא דכתובה mamona de'kesuvah when it comes to, okay, does he
have to pay the כתובה? kesuvah? Our answer is no, he doesn't
have to pay the כתובה. kesuvah. That's a question of ממון mamon
and therefore we say המוציא מחברו עליו הראיה. hamotzi mechavero alav hara'aya.
If she wants to collect her כתובה, kesuvah, she's going to have
to prove that the קידושין kiddushin was binding. And we're not sure
the קידושין kiddushin was binding, it might have been קידושי טעות. kiddushei
ta'os. But גבי איסורא לחומרא, gabi issura lachumra, does he have to
give a גט? get? Yes, we're going to be strict, it might
have been a binding קידושין kiddushin and we're going to demand a
גט. get. So basically exactly, ספק ממזרות, safek mamzerus, ספק אשת איש.
safek eshes ish. So basically we're saying this middle ground that it
is, is that the case in the end is that there was
no תנאי tnai ever said, but a woman having vows is not
a desirable situation for the man, and therefore he has to give
her a גט get but not pay the כתובה. kesuvah. How do
you explain that middle level? So the גמרא Gemara basically says it's
a ספק קידושי טעות. safek kiddushei ta'os. It might not have been
a קידושין kiddushin all altogether. So since it might have been, he
has to give her a גט. get. Since it might not have
been, he doesn't have to give her a כתובה. kesuvah. Now what
I want to point out is that I find it in all
honesty very strange that the גמרא Gemara does not have to say
it's a ספק safek and doesn't recognize a possible middle level of
הקפדה. hakpadah. Like there's some things, like you go ahead and you
buy a car, right? It turns out that the, I don't know,
that the transmission was basically almost dead, okay, or something like major.
You could say the whole thing is a קידושי טעות, kiddushei ta'os,
right? Okay, or מקח טעות, mekach ta'os, excuse me. מקח טעות. Mekach
ta'os.
You go ahead and you buy the car and you buy it
and you find out, I don't know, that the exactly, the CD
player is not functioning or whatever. So it's not a מקח טעות,
mekach ta'os, but you're entitled to get reimbursement or to get it
exchanged, right? There could be like a middle level of הקפדה. hakpadah.
You could say, look, I wouldn't say that I wouldn't want to
be married under those circumstances, but
it was enough not what I wanted that I should be entitled
to divorce her without paying the כתובה. kesuvah. The same way if
there's certain behavior that occurs in the marriage, it's a basis for
divorce without a כתובה kesuvah because she's to blame, it's enough of
a reason for a divorce at
true fault for that I should be entitled not to pay the
כתובה, kesuvah, but it doesn't mean that it's not binding. So it's
binding at all. So it's funny that the גמרא Gemara doesn't think,
doesn't deal with the possibility of an intermediate situation. Now I'll remind
you, remember the discussion at the beginning of the מסכת, maseches, right?
It turns out she's not a בתולה, besulah, he thought she was
a בתולה, besulah, right? So what does that mean? If he thought
she was a בתולה besulah and she wasn't, does it mean that
they were never married and she doesn't need a גט? get? Or
does it mean no, no, she needs a גט, get, but maybe
she was מופחתת מכתובה, mufcheses miksuvah, right? So the גמרא Gemara there
dealt with the possibility that it was a binding קידושין, kiddushin, but
because it wasn't exactly what he expected, he might be entitled to
divorce her without having to pay the כתובה. kesuvah. You never said,
I'm not really married.
Like you wouldn't say, it just turns out I'm not really married.
I didn't really buy the car.
Right, the car is yours, but he has to replace the thing.
Right, right. So in terms of, you'd say like the whole thing
is done
under false pretenses and it was never binding to begin with, but
there's a middle level where of course the basic things were there
and it is binding, but there is some blame and fault and
there's some consequences to it. So it's very strange that the גמרא
Gemara sort of does not deal with that as a middle case.
Anyway, now the גמרא Gemara continues. Okay, so we have this debate
of רב ושמואל Rav u'Shmuel and about
whether when the original קידושין kiddushin wasn't binding, whether it's תנאי tnai
or it was קטנה ketanah or whatever, and then they continue to
live together, is that itself considered to be that now they are
married. I have a methodological question. Yeah. Doesn't the גמרא Gemara do
this too? In other words, it gives out the polarities, the extremes
and it gives you space to. No, the גמרא Gemara asks the
question, how could it be that you need a גט get and
you don't pay the כתובה? kesuvah? It gives two answers. One, you
need a גט דרבנן, get derabbanan, or it's a ספק. safek. But
the obvious third answer, which is, it's bad enough
to deprive of כתובה, kesuvah, but not so bad to mean that
it's not קידושין. kiddushin. Methodologically, it means that the גמרא Gemara wants
to limit you to those two options? Exactly. I mean, I don't
want someone to move here not in a pure theoretical Torah about-life
discussion,
but it's interesting that the גמרא Gemara raises the question and doesn't
give what to us would seem like, I think, an obvious answer.
All right, the גמרא Gemara says like this, אמר רבא, Amar Rava,
now that we've laid this out, now we're going to get a
series of later אמוראים Amoraim that are going to try to frame
and possibly limit the debate of רב ושמואל. Rav u'Shmuel. We only
had one initial approach that just explained to us whether רב Rav
was saying that the continued sex is an act of קידושין kiddushin
or whether he's מוחל mochel on the תנאי. tnai. But now we're
going to get
אמוראים Amoraim like serious, weighty, of where the debate would be, trying
to say no, no, this case they already agree on, the debate's
in this case, in a way of sort of trying to frame
which is the, which are the issues that רב ושמואל Rav u'Shmuel
really disagree on. Okay, and we're going to see a couple of
different approaches to this. So let's take a look.
אמר רבא, Amar Rava, says רבא, Rava, מחלוקת בטעות שני נשים. machlokes
b'taos shtei nashim. The debate is when there are two women. אבל
בטעות אשה אחת, Aval b'taos isha achas, but with only one woman
with this mistake, as there was a condition which wasn't met, דברי
הכל. אינה צריכה הימנו גט. divrei hakol eina tzericha heimenu get, She
definitely doesn't need a גט. get. Meaning if it's the simple case
where it says man made a condition with one woman at the
קידושין, kiddushin, no נדרים, nedarim, have the נישואין, nissu'in, slept together, turned
out נדרים. nedarim. So that everybody would agree the original תנאי tnai
made with the first woman, made with this woman, is considered to
be implicitly continued after the time of the חופה chuppah and the
נישואין nissu'in and the sex. And if that תנאי tnai isn't met,
they're not married. Of course the תנאי tnai continues to be binding.
So then what's the debate of רב Rav and שמואל? Shmuel? The
debate of רב Rav and שמואל Shmuel is that there were two
women. He made a condition with one woman and then he married
a second woman without the condition. And the debate is do we
assume that the condition he made with רחל, Rachel, because he said
it with רחל, Rachel, should also implicitly be the condition he made
with לאה? Leah? Okay, which is clearly not what it sounded like
for רב Rav and שמואל, Shmuel, but that's what he's saying. He
wants to say that if it was just רחל Rachel and he
made the condition at the קידושין, kiddushin, of course everybody agrees it
continues even through the נישואין. nissu'in. Okay, so let's take a look.
אבל באשה אחת דברי הכל אינה צריכה הימנו גט. aval b'isha achas
divrei hakol eina tzericha heimenu get. Okay, but if only one woman,
of course the condition remains binding. So אמר אביי, amar Abaye, so
אביי Abaye said it. והא מתניתין, ve'ha matnisin, one minute, our משנה,
mishna, באשה אחת היא, b'isha achas hi, it was just about one
woman, right? He made a, he did a קידושין kiddushin and then
a נישואין, nissu'in, right, our case in the משנה. mishna. וקמותבינן שיושתינהי,
v'kamosvinan sheyoshinehi, and just in the earlier passage of the גמרא, Gemara,
we challenged שמואל's Shmuel's position based on our משנה, mishna, right? That's
just what we got through. So clearly, you know, it seems like
the consensus, רש"י Rashi says okay, but that who, you know, who
says that what we said before was the right interpretation. But רש"י
Rashi is just saying look, nobody knows exactly what the debate, you
know, what the context of רב Rav and שמואל's Shmuel's debate is.
We're speculating, is it in this case or from that case and
so on. But it seems רש"י Rashi says that, you know, there's
been an implicit consensus in the way we've been learning it because
we bring in our משנה mishna to challenge שמואל's Shmuel's position, that
we're assuming that their debate is just about one woman because our
משנה mishna is one woman and you know we have a tradition
that that's relevant to this debate and that we've challenged שמואל's Shmuel's
position. So you can't say that they're only debating the case of
two, of two women.
So he goes back to the case of the two women.
He marries רחל Rachel with the condition that there are
no נדרים nedarim and that condition remains binding even through the נישואין
nissu'in because everybody agrees according to this claim that the condition at
the קידושין kiddushin remains binding through the נישואין. nissu'in. But then he
marries לאה Leah without saying anything. Do we assume that with לאה
Leah also it was only under the condition that there were no
נדרים? nedarim? A completely right, strange explanation so אביי Abaye rejects it.
He says no, that אביי Abaye says it can't be. Clearly רב
Rav and שמואל Shmuel are relevant, you know, we challenge them with
our משנה, mishna, or שמואל Shmuel with our משנה. mishna. Clearly we're
talking about one woman. אלא אי אתמר הכי אתמר, ella ei itmar
hachi itmar, rather this is how it was said. אמר רבא מחלוקת
באשה אחת כעין שתי נשים. amar Rava machlokes b'isha achas k'ein shtei
nashim. Fine. So he's going to try to still maintain this a
little bit. The debate one woman, that's true, but only if it's
like the case of two women. אבל באשה אחת גרידתא, aval b'isha
achas geridta, but if it's just a simple case of one woman,
קידושין על תנאי ונישואין, kiddushin al tnai v'nissu'in, דברי הכל divrei hakol.
אינה צריכה הימנו גט, eina tzericha heimenu get. everybody would say that
she doesn't need a גט. get. So רבא Rava still wants to
say that he thinks, and again this is again very relevant right
for the עגונה agunah issue, because he thinks that everybody would say
in a normal case, a קידושין על תנאי kiddushin al tnai remains,
that תנאי tnai remains in effect through the נישואין. nissu'in. Everybody would
say that, even רב Rav and שמואל. Shmuel. According to his take.
So when does רב Rav say that, that the woman needs a
גט, get, right? As if it's a marriage even though there's a
תנאי? tnai? It's like two women. What's like two women? So רש"י
Rashi says the case is like this: I married רחל Rachel על
תנאי. al tnai. Then we didn't find out whether there was, the
תנאי tnai was met or wasn't met or whatever it was. Anyway,
then I divorced her, okay, before we even had the חופה. chuppah.
Okay, we've had a rocky relationship me and רחל. Rachel. Then we
decide we're going to go through with it again. And we do
another קידושין kiddushin and a חופה. chuppah. The second time around I
don't remake the תנאי. tnai. So do we assume that the תנאי
tnai I made with her the first time we got married remains
to be the תנאי tnai the second time we got married? This
is, this is crazy right? This is the פשט pshat of רב
Rav and שמואל. Shmuel. But the point being, you know, it's obviously
not the פשט pshat of רב Rav and שמואל, Shmuel, but he's
really trying to say it seems, he really says, look, if there's
a תנאי tnai at קידושין, kiddushin, it should remain binding at the
time of the נישואין. nissu'in. And if it sounds like רב Rav
says not like that, we're going to have to try to bracket
רב Rav and say that he's talking about a strange case. But
if it's a normal case, a תנאי tnai at קידושין kiddushin remains
binding at the time of the נישואין. nissu'in. And because he's saying
something, you know, do we assume that... Right. So let's see. איתיביה
אביי, aisaivei Abaye, so אביי Abaye asked him this. קידשה בטעות ובפחות
משוה פרוטה, kiddashah b'taus u'v'pachos mishaveh pruta, we learn in a ברייתא,
braisa, if a man married a woman in error or with a,
with something that turned out less than a פרוטה. pruta. וכן קטן
שקידש, v'chein katan shekiddesh, or a minor married. All these cases it
wasn't a legitimate קידושין. kiddushin. אף על
פי ששלח סבלונות לאחר מכאן,
af al pi sheshalach sivlonos
l'achar mikan, even though after the minor became an adult or whatever
the person sent these סבלונות, sivlonos, which are like gifts. the bride's
family and to the bride or whatever, אינה מקודשת. einah mekudeshet. We
don't consider those gifts to now be new כסף קידושין. kessef kidushin.
שמחמת קידושין הראשון שלח, shemachmat kidushin harishon shalach, because he thought that
the קידושין kidushin was binding and the practice is after the קידושין
kidushin before the נישואין nisuin you send nice gifts, but nobody is
intending that to be a new מעשה קידושין. maaseh kidushin. Now, fine.
ואם בעלו, v'im baalu, but if they went ahead and had sex
after for example the minor became an adult or whatever the case
might be, then קנו, kanu, then the act of sex is binding.
So this seems exactly relevant. The original קידושין kidushin wasn't binding, but
after the act of sex it is binding. What רבן בן גמליאל
Rabban ben Gamliel says משום רבי ישמעאל mishum Rabbi Yishmael אומר, omer,
אם בעלו לא קנו. im baalu lo kanu. No, this act of
sex is not binding. So this is exactly the debate of רב
Rav and שמואל, Shmuel, right? There wasn't an original קידושין kidushin and
then there was sex. Do you say that that creates a קידושין
kidushin or not? מחלוקת תנאים. machloket tannaim. So the גמרא Gemara says,
and the גמרא Gemara solves that. דהכא דבטעות אישה אחת היא. d'hacha
d'b'taut isha achat hi. It's all about one woman, right? That one
woman like two women. It's one woman, it's not a good קידושין,
kidushin, then sex. ופליגי, u'pligi, and we see that they debate. Does
the sex become
קידושין? kidushin? You know. So מאי לאו טעות ותנאי. mai lav taut
v'tnai. Now presumably this is the same case about the case of
vows. And when it says the original קידושין kidushin was בטעות, b'taut,
presumably it means like this issue of vows, like that was done
by a condition and the
condition... okay, that's a good point. And the condition wasn't met. So
רבה Rabba says no, no, not necessarily case of vows. טעות פחות
משווה פרוטה. taut pachot mishaveh pruta. It meant a case for example
it was less than a פרוטה. pruta. So the גמרא Gemara says,
now why that should be different we'll see in a minute. But
first let's understand if that's the case of the ברייתא. braita. So
the גמרא Gemara says פחות משווה פרוטה, pachot mishaveh pruta, wait a
minute, less than a פרוטה, pruta, והא תני לה. v'ha tani lah.
Wait, that's explicit in this ברייתא. braita. It says קידושין בטעות kidushin
b'taut case number one, ופחות משווה פרוטה u'pachot mishaveh pruta case number
two. So טעות taut has to mean something else. Presumably טעות taut
would mean like רב Rav and שמואל, Shmuel, a condition that wasn't
met. So the גמרא Gemara
says no. פירושי קמפרש. perushei kamfaresh. It's explained like this: קידושין בטעות.
kidushin b'taut. What's a case that was an error? כגון כיצד? kegon
keitzad? How is it? כגון שקידש בפחות משווה פרוטה. kegon shekidesh b'pachot
mishaveh pruta. For example, less than a פרוטה pruta or a minor,
etc. So what the גמרא Gemara is saying is that you're right,
this is a case if the sex constitutes afterwards constitutes קידושין, kidushin,
but it's not the case of a תנאי. tnai. It's the case
of a טעות. taut. There is a mistake. Like you thought you
were married, but it turned out you weren't. Why did you think
you were married? Because you thought that the ring was worth a
פרוטה pruta but it wasn't, or you thought that the guy was
an adult and it turned out he was a minor. So there's
a difference between a mistake and a תנאי. tnai. And now the
גמרא Gemara is going to explain the difference, okay? So the גמרא
Gemara says like this: במאי קמיפלגי? b'mai kamiflagi? What's the debate in
that ברייתא? braita? מר סבר אדם יודע שאין קידושין תופסין בפחות משווה
פרוטה. mar savar adam yodeia she'ein kidushin tofsin b'pachot mishaveh pruta. A
person knows that the original קידושין kidushin wasn't good because it was
less than a פרוטה, pruta, it was a minor, וגמר ובעל לשם
קידושין. v'gamar u'baal l'shem kidushin. And therefore the sex is intended to
be an act of קידושין kidushin because there's a knowledge that the
original act wasn't binding. ומר סבר, u'mar savar, the other one holds,
אין אדם יודע שאין קידושין תופסין בפחות משווה פרוטה. ein adam yodeia
she'ein kidushin tofsin b'pachot mishaveh pruta. No, there's no reason to assume
that they knew the original act wasn't binding. And since they assumed
it
was, וכי קא בעל, v'chi ka baal,
then even the later act of sex, אדעתא דקידושין הראשונים בעל, adaata
d'kidushin harishonim baal, is all defined in the context of the original
קידושין. kidushin. And since the original קידושין kidushin wasn't binding, this is
not a new act of קידושין, kidushin, and therefore they're not remarried
now. So what the גמרא Gemara is saying is it's really important
to step back and
appreciate conceptually two different cases. One is, the original קידושין kidushin wasn't
binding for whatever reason, sort of like before we had she was
a minor, he was a minor, it was less than a פרוטה.
pruta. Okay, and there's one thing to say that, okay, so therefore
you know it's possible that the act of sex would be a
new act of קידושין kidushin because maybe they're aware that that thing
wasn't good and you still want and you're still living together and
having sex together, that itself should constitute a new act of קידושין.
kidushin. But if the guy explicitly said, "I only want to marry
you on the condition of A, B, and C," then even if
they continue having sex together, says the גמרא, Gemara, that condition should
frame their continued sexual life, their continued life together. He made it
explicit he only wants it under this condition. So that is the
claim. The claim is that I, says רבה, Rabba, I claim that
even רב Rav who says that the act of sex creates קידושין,
kidushin, that is not when the תנאי tnai is explicit and we're
dealing with a simple case of one woman. If the תנאי tnai
is explicit and it's a case of one woman, even the continued
living together and sex is all framed by the original תנאי. tnai.
Doesn't matter, you said a תנאי, tnai, that תנאי tnai makes it
clear it's only under those conditions. Let's do one more case. איתיבי,
eitivei, one more case.
הריני בועליך, hareini boalayich, a man says to a woman, "I'm going
to have sex with you," על מנת שירצה אבא, al m'nat sheyirtzeh
abba, "on the condition that your father agrees to the marriage." Okay,
now we're not asking for first... although this act of sex will
be... no, it's right. I'm having sex with you regardless of whether
your father... I'm having sex with you and it'll be an act
of קידושין kiddushin if the father agrees to the marriage. Okay.
So, אף על פי שלא רצה האב, af al pi shelo ratza
ha'av, even if the father in the end did not agree to
the קידושין, kiddushin, מקודשת, mekudeshet, they're still married. Because why? He
said על מנת. al mnat. ומשום רבי ישמעאל ברבי יוסי אומר, umishum
Rabbi Yishmael b'Rabbi Yose omer, אב
לא רצה מקודשת, av lo ratza mekudeshet, and ומשום רבי יהודה אומר
umishum Rabbi Yehuda omer says no, if you made a condition, if
the father agrees she's מקודשת, mekudeshet, and if לא רצה, lo ratza,
he didn't agree, אינה מקודשת. eina mekudeshet. Now, why should the first
thing say they're married regardless? It must be that even though you
make a תנאי, tnai, you go ahead and you have sex. The
sex overrides the תנאי. tnai. So the גמרא Gemara says והכא בחדא
איתתא דמי, vehacha bachada iteta dami, it's one woman, there's a condition,
and even though there's a condition, once there's sex, that it's possible
that that defines them as married.
ופליגי, u'pligi, and that's the debate of רב Rav and שמואל. Shmuel.
Condition and then sex, according to one opinion, they're married regardless now
that they've had sex. The גמרא Gemara says no, התם דהא קמיפלגי,
hatam deha kamiflagi, there this is what the debate was. מר סבר,
Mar savar, על מנת שירצה אבא, al mnat sheyirtze abba, the question
is what does it mean when he says on the condition that
your father agrees? One says what it means is על מנת שישתוק
אב, al mnat sheyishtok av, on the condition that he doesn't object.
Okay, and the case would be that the father didn't object or
he didn't agree. Okay, so we're reading this into the case. ושתק
ליה, v'shatak lei, he didn't object, so therefore they're married.
The fact that the father agrees means as long as he doesn't
object. ומר סבר, U'mar savar, and the other one says no. על
מנת שיאמר אבא הן, al mnat sheyomar abba hen, on the condition
he agrees means that he has to agree, say yes, I'm okay
with it. והא לא אמר אבא הן, veha lo amar abba hen,
and he didn't say yes. Now again, the ברייתא braita is not
at all clear in the משנה Mishnah that that was what the
issue was, I mean the ברייתא braita should have said it. Okay,
but basically what you're having is that it seems that we're having
these debates about whether something that wasn't a קידושין kiddushin initially, but
followed by sex, does the sex define them as being married? It
seems that this is a debate of רב Rav and שמואל Shmuel
and a debate of תנאים. Tannaim. But רבא Raba wants to say,
maybe it's one thing to have that issue when there wasn't an
explicit condition. But when there's an explicit condition, it should all be
framed by the explicit condition. And the fact that רב Rav seems
to say that even there they're married, he wants to sort of
reinterpret רב. Rav. Okay, so this is one approach to limit the
debate of רב Rav and שמואל, Shmuel, to limit this when it's
a not a good קידושין, kiddushin, but not an explicit condition. Then
it's possible that the living together as a married couple makes them
married. But in an explicit condition, רבא Raba's contention is the debate
would always define what and therefore if that condition wasn't met, they
would never wind up being married. Okay, so we'll continue this tomorrow.
What's the difference between making...